Guide to the Hersey Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Hersey Family Papers
1860-1952
1906-1942
YCAL MSS 723
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.29
(8 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
Collection contains correspondence and other materials relating to the family of American novelist and author John Hersey. Correspondence contains letters from John Hersey and members of the Hersey and Baird families. There are letters from John Hersey to his parents dating from his graduate studies in Cambridge, England, in 1936 and 1937, to dispatches written as a war correspondent, in 1942, while in the South Pacific. Other materials include various family papers, such as John's school books, a copy of his undergraduate thesis, "The Letters of John Trumbull," clippings and printed ephemera, photographs, and manuscript notes by Roscoe Monroe Hersey. Photograph albums contain images of China, circa 1907 and 1908, the Hersey family, and France in WWI, and a scrapbook documents the lives of Hersey children, starting in 1912
Hersey family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Charles Apfelbaum on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund, 1994.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
John Hersey Papers. Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Hersey Family
Roscoe Monroe Hersey (1878-) and Grace Baird Hersey (1882-1966) were missionaries in Tientsin, China, where Roscoe worked as a secretrary for the Young Men's Christian Association. The Hersey family returned to the United States in 1925 and settled in Briarcliff Manor, New York. After they returned to the U.S.,their son John Richard Hersey (1914-1993), the novelist and author, attended public school, Hotchkiss School, Yale University, and Clare College, Cambridge before working as a journalist, first for Time magazine (1937-1944), and then as a correspondent and editor for Life and The New Yorker.
Biographical information taken from "Hersey, John Richard." The Scribner Encyclopedia of American Lives. Ed. Kenneth T. Jackson, Karen Markoe, and Arnold Markoe. Vol. 3: 1991-1993. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 2001. 268-270. Biography In Context. Web. 8 April 2013.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence and other materials relating to the family of American novelist and author John Hersey. Correspondence consists of letters from John Hersey and other members of the Hersey and Baird families to Roscoe Monroe and Grace Baird Hersey. There are letters from John Hersey to his parents dating from his graduate studies in Cambridge, England, in 1936 and 1937, to dispatches written as a war correspondent, in 1942, while in the South Pacific. Other materials include various family papers, such as John's school books, a copy of his undergraduate thesis, "The Letters of John Trumbull," clippings and printed ephemera, photographs, and manuscript notes by Roscoe Monroe Hersey. Photograph albums contain images of China, circa 1907 and 1908, the Hersey family, and France in WWI, and a scrapbook documents the lives of Hersey children starting in 1912.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1881-1942. II. Other Materials, 1860-1952.
Language(s)
Chiefly in English; some material in Chinese.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; World War, 1914-1918 -- France -- Pictorial works; China -- Pictorial works; Photographic prints; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Hersey, Grace Baird; Hersey, John, 1914-1993; Hersey, Roscoe Monroe; Trumbull, John, 1750-1831; Hersey family
- Correspondence, 1881-1942; Series I; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence contains letters from John Hersey and other members of the Hersey and Baird families. The series features letters from John Hersey to his parents dating from his graduate studies in Cambridge, England, in 1936 and 1937, to dispatches written as a war correspondent, in 1942, while in the South Pacific.
  - Baird, Ella, 1919-1924 (Box 1)
  - Baird, John, 1920, undated (Box 1)
  - Baird, W., 1881-1917, undated; 7 (Box 1)
  - Hersey, Arthur, 1920 June (Box 1)
  - Hersey, Grace Baird, 1920-1923 (Box 1)
  - Hersey, John, 1936-1942, undated; 6 (Box 2)
  - [Hersey?], Rob, 1935-1936, undated; 2 (Box 2)
  - Hersey, Roscoe Monroe, 1911-1942, undated (Box 2)
  - Hersey, Roscoe Jr., 1920, undated (Box 2)
  - Others, 1897-1942 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified, 1916-1922, undated (Box 2)
- Other Materials, 1860-1952; Series II; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series II. Other Materials includes various family papers, such as John's school books, a copy of his undergraduate thesis, "The Letters of John Trumbull," clippings and printed ephemera, photographs, and manuscript notes by Roscoe Monroe Hersey. Photograph albums contain images of China, circa 1907 and 1908, the Hersey family, and France in WWI, and a scrapbook documents the lives of Hersey children, including John, starting in 1912.
  - Catalogue of Paintings by Colonel Trumbull, printed version, 1860 (Box 3)
  - Certificates, 1904-1905
  - Chinese Triangles, printed version, 1924 (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 1919-1955, undated (Box 3)
  - John Hersey schoolbooks, 1925-1925 (Box 3)
  - "John R. Hersey Violin" lesson book, undated (Box 3)
  - "The Letters of John Trumbull Relating to the Affairs of the World of the Period 1778-1814," edited and correlated by John R. Hersey, [circa 1936] (Box 3)
  - Medical records, [1911?] (Box 3)
  - Manuscript notes, undated (Box 3)
  - Our Village: Briarcliffe Manor, N. Y. 1902 to 1952, printed version, inscribed (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1923-1939 (Box 3)
  - Photograph albums, 1907-1939 (Box 4)
  - Pin and cutout, undated (Box 4)
  - Printed ephemera, 1905-1952, undated (Box 4)
  - Roscoe M. Hersey papers, 1906-1922, undated; 5 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1912-1923, undated
  - Tientsin YMCA material, 1909-1930, undated (Box 4)
- Oversize, 0.83; (3 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
  - Empty envelopes (In Series I), undated (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - Empty envelope (In Series I), undated (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - Certificates (In Series II), 1904-1905 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - Photographs (In Series II), 1923-1924 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - Printed ephemera (In Series II), 1944, 1946; 2 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - Clippings (In Series II), 1924-1943 (Box 6 (Broadside))
  - Photograph album (In Series II), [circa 1914] (Box 7 (Oversize))
  - Scrapbook (In Series II), 1912-1923, undated (Box 8 (Oversize))